Finding Aid for the Stafford Leak Warren Papers LSC.0987
UCLA Library Special Collections
Stafford Leak Warren papers
1917-1980
1943-1980
UCLA Library Special Collections
Warren, Stafford L. (Stafford Leak), 1896-1981
LSC.0987
148.0 linear feet (281 boxes, 8 cartons, 26 oversize boxes, and 1 oversize folder)
Stafford Leak Warren was the director of the Atomic Energy Project at the University of Rochester and worked on the Manhattan Project. After the war, Warren came to UCLA to serve as Dean of the School of Medicine and as Vice-Chancellor of the Health Sciences. The collection consists of Warren's professional papers, documenting every major phase of his career. The bulk of the papers cover 1940 onward, including Warren's participation in the Manhattan Project and Operation Crossroads, and his subsequent involvement concerning issues and work with atomic bomb development and radiation effects.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Operation Crossroads papers and Manhattan Project papers are available for access on 35 mm positive microfilm (in boxes 303-305) in Library Special Collections. Originals, stored in boxes 57-83, not available for consultation due to fragile condition.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This collection contains both processed and unprocessed audiovisual materials. Audiovisual materials are not currently available for access, unless otherwise noted in a Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note at the series and file levels. All requests to access processed audiovisual materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942327183606533
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Dr. Stafford L. Warren, date of receipt unknown. Gift of Gertrude Warren, 1982. Addition to the collection gift of Jane Larson, 1987.
Almost all the papers of Stafford Leak Warren were donated to the UCLA Library on April 19, 1982 by his widow, Mrs. Gertrude Warren. A small number of items, consisting mostly of government publications and materials relating to Dr. Warren's research interests at the University of Rochester and his work on mental retardation as Special Advisor to Presidents John F. Kennedy and Lyndon B. Johnson, were received in the 1960s, when records relating to his foundational service as Dean of the UCLA School of Medicine, were transferred to the University Archives.
Biography
Stafford Leak Warren was born on June 19, 1896 in Maxwell City, New Mexico. In 1918, Warren earned his Bachelor of Arts degree from University of California at Berkeley. Then in 1922, Warren received his Master of Arts in Research Medicine and simultaneously obtained his Doctors of Medicine degree from the University of California, San Francisco Medical School. From 1922-1925, Warren completed his post-doctoral work at both Johns Hopkins University and Harvard University. Then in 1926, Warren became an Assistant Professor in the Department of Radiology at the University of Rochester. Subsequently, Warren became an Associate Professor of Medicine in 1930 and remained at the University of Rochester until 1943. During his residence at the University of Rochester, Warren performed groundbreaking research on radiology and its ability to track cancer in breasts. Through his research he developed a stereoscopic technique used to detect breast cancer in women which eventually led to the invention of the mammogram.
Before departing from the University of Rochester in 1943, Warren was briefly the university's Director of the Atomic Energy Project. Within the same year, Warren was commissioned as a Colonel in the United States Army Medical Corps and became chief of the medical section and advisor to the director of the Manhattan Project, which dealt with the research and development of the atomic bomb during World War II. From 1943-1946, Warren worked on the safety aspects surrounding the Manhattan Project, Trinity Nuclear tests, and Operation Crossroads. During the Trinity Nuclear tests, Warren's primary responsibility was medical research, but he also supervised the project's health and safety programs. When Operation Crossroads began testing on the Marshall Islands to investigate the effect of nuclear weapons on warships, Warren planned and implemented procedures to evaluate, limit, and control the impact of radiation. However after these tests, Warren became aware of the radioactive contamination in the environment and warned the public about the potential dangers of the atomic bomb. In 1947, Warren was awarded the Distinguished Service Medal and Legion of Merit for his service on the Manhattan Project. During 1947, Warren helped establish the University of California at Los Angeles' new School of Medicine. Warren also served as the school's first Dean until 1963 when he became Vice-Chancellor of Health Services from 1963-1965. During the 1960s, Warren was a Special Advisor who helped research the effects of mental retardation on behalf of U.S. Presidents John F. Kennedy and Lyndon B. Johnson.
After Warren's first wife, Viola Lockhart's death in 1968, he remarried in 1970 to Gertrude Turner Hubberty. In 1972, Warren received the Enrico Fermi Award from the Atomic Energy Commission. Warren held the position of Professor Emeritus at UCLA from 1965 until his death. Stafford Leak Warren died on July 26, 1981 in Pacific Palisades, California.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of Warren's professional papers, documenting every major phase of his career. Materials include glass slides, photographs and materials assembled in connection with Warren's research. His research included fever therapy, arthritis, and the effects of shock. The bulk of the papers cover 1940 onward, including Warren's participation in the Manhattan Project and Operation Crossroads, and his subsequent involvement concerning issues and work with atomic bomb development and radiation effects. Warren's contribution to the Manhattan Project and Operation Crossroads produced a series of photographs of the test area and effects of the bomb such as clippings of blast waves and radiation, and a motion picture in relation to the project on microfilm.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of these materials are available for viewing in the Library Special Collections Ahmanson-Murphy Reading Room.
Related Material
An Exceptional Man for Exceptional Challenges [oral history transcript] / Stafford L. Warren, interviewee. UCLA Oral History Department interview, 1983. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
University of California, Los Angeles. School of Medicine. Administrative files of Stafford L. Warren, 1925-1968. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Viola Lockhart Warren Papers (Collection 1322). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Governor Earl Warren, UCLA Medical School Dean Stafford L. Warren, and UC Regent Edward A. Dickson, ca. 1951 (online image)
Nuclear energy -- Research.; College administrators -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Physicians -- United States -- Archives.; Mental retardation -- Research.; Atomic bomb -- Physiological effect -- Research.; Manhattan Project (U.S.).; Operation Crossroads, 1946; Warren, Stafford L. (Stafford Leak), 1896-1981--Archives.
- I. University of Rochester Papers.
  General note
  (See also Box 227 and oversize packages 1 and 11 below)
  - Research materials. (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3, Box 4, Box 5, Box 6, Box 7, Box 8, Box 9, Box 10, Box 11, Box 12, Box 13, Box 14, Box 15, Box 16, Box 17, Box 18, Box 19, Box 20)
    Scope and Contents note
    re SLW's work on arthritis, fever therapy and the effects of shock.
    Box 4 includes correspondence and papers relating to the War Research Committee, 1942-43.
  - Glass slides relating to medical research. (Box 21)
  - Correspondence between SLW and the University of Rochester, 1943-46, correspondence and miscellany., 1917-18. (Box 21)
    Transferred from the papers of SLW's first wife, Viola Warren (Collection 1322).
  - Glass slides relating to medical research. (Box 22, Box 23)
  - Offprints and other research materials. (Box 24, Box 25, Box 26, Box 27, Box 28, Box 29, Box 30, Box 31, Box 32, Box 33, Box 34, Box 35, Box 36, Box 37, Box 38, Box 39, Box 40, Box 41, Box 42, Box 43, Box 44, Box 45, Box 46, Box 47, Box 48, Box 49, Box 50, Box 51, Box 52)
    re SLW's research interests at the University of Rochester.
    Includes SLW's correspondence files as Treasurer of the American Neisserian Medical Society, 1940-41 (Box 30).
  - Offprints, Rochester reprints., 1925-49. (Box 53, Box 54, Box 55, Box 56)
- II. Manhattan Engineering District Papers.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Originals, stored in boxes 57-83, not available for consultation due to fragile condition. These materials are, instead, available for access on 35 mm positive microfilm in boxes 303-305.
  (See also Section 4 and oversize packages 2, 3 and 12 below)
  - Enlistment Materials for SLW., November 1943.
    - 1. Identification wallet containing U.S. Government badge. (Box 57, Folder 1)
      Originals not available for consultation due to fragile condition. These materials are available for access on 35 mm positive microfilm in boxes 303-305.
    - 2. Copy memo, Major General the Adjutant General to SLW., November 2, 1943.; (2 duplicates). (Box 57, Folder 1)
    - 3. Memo, Adjutant General to SLW., November 30, 1943. (Box 57, Folder 1)
    - 4. Copy report of physical examination of SLW., September 30, 1943. (Box 57, Folder 1)
    - 5. Copy memo, R.W. Pulliam, Captain, Corps of Engineers, Military Personnel Officer to the Adjutant General., December 17, 1943. (Box 57, Folder 1)
      Originals, stored in boxes 57-83, not available for consultation due to fragile condition. These materials are available for access on 35 mm positive microfilm (in boxes 303-305).
    - 6. Copy information sheet for newly appointed army officers., undated; (5pp.). (Box 57, Folder 1)
    - 7. Business card, Arnold Kramish, R. and D. Associates., undated (Box 57, Folder 1)
    - 8. Copy War Department release relating to SLW., undated (Box 57, Folder 1)
  - Note, Prescription and Memo., April, July, August 1945.; 3 items:
    - 1. Rough notes, questions and answers for General Groves, by SLW., April 17, 1945.; (3pp.). (Box 57, Folder 2)
    - 2. Prescription for Jules Vieoux., July 1, 1945. (Box 57, Folder 2)
    - 3. Copy memo [report] with tables, composition of Monitoring Company, Colonel L.E. Seeman to Major General Groves., August 4, 1945.; (7pp. total). (Box 57, Folder 2)
  - Radioactive Materials Forms., December 1945.; 3 items:
    - 1. Copy application for radioactive materials, National Research Council., December 4, 1945.; (2pp.). (Box 57, Folder 3)
    - 2. Copy form letter, M.A. Tuve, National Research Council to individuals engaged in radioactive research., December 4, 1945. (Box 57, Folder 3)
    - 3. Messages for SLW., undated (Box 57, Folder 3)
  - Assorted Notes and Letters., December 1945-January 1946.; 8 items:
    - 1. Rough notes, meeting of working committee, by SLW., December 1, 1945.; (9pp.). (Box 57, Folder 4)
    - 2. Copy rough notes, meeting of working committee, by SLW., December 1, 1945.; (9pp.). (Box 57, Folder 4)
    - 3. Rough notes, Russian concerns., December 1, 1945.; (2pp.). (Box 57, Folder 4)
    - 4. Memo routing slip to Major General Groves., December 1, 1945. (Box 57, Folder 4)
    - 5. Rough notes, comments on the Atomic Energy Commission., January 3, 1946.; (4pp.). (Box 57, Folder 4)
    - 6. Copy rough notes, Manhattan District declassification, by SLW., undated (Box 57, Folder 4)
    - 7. Copy letter, SLW to Colonel McCrae., January 3, 1946.; (8pp.). (Box 57, Folder 4)
    - 8. Rough letter, SLW to Colonel McCrae., January 3, 1946.; (12pp.). (Box 57, Folder 4)
  - Letter and Enclosure., 1946.; 2 items:
    - 1. Letter, J.H. Lawrence, M.D., to SLW., May 10, 1946. (Box 57, Folder 5)
    - 2. Copy list, chapter authors., undated (Box 57, Folder 5)
  - Assorted army pay records, travel vouchers and travel orders., May 1943-May 1945.; 101 items. (Box 57, Folder 6)
  - Assorted army pay records, travel vouchers and travel orders., May 1944-December 1944.; 97 items. (Box 57, Folder 7)
  - Assorted army pay records, travel vouchers and travel orders., January 1945-December 1945.; 105 items. (Box 57, Folder 8)
  - Assorted army pay records, travel vouchers and travel orders., December 1946-April 1947.; 71 items. (Box 57, Folder 9)
  - Copy lecture, address of SLW before the American Pharmaceutical Association (21pp.)., August 12, 1948.; 1 item. (Box 57, Folder 10)
  - Reports, Nuclear Energy/Public Health., September 1948.; 3 items:
    - 1. The Influence of Modern Developments in Nuclear Energy on Public Health Problems, by SLW., September 9, 1948.; (2 duplicates, 4pp. each). (Box 57, Folder 11)
      Reprint from Centennial, American Association for the Advancement of Science.
    - Copy report, World Health Problems: the Influence of Modern Developments in Nuclear Energy on Public Health Problems., September 9, 1948.; (18pp.). (Box 57, Folder 11)
      Originals, stored in boxes 57-83, not available for consultation due to fragile condition. These materials are available for access on 35 mm positive microfilm (in boxes 303-305). Materials include a revised copy of this report dated May 11, 1949.
  - Report, Bomb Irradiation, With Letter., May 12, 1948.; 2 items:
    - 1. Letter, W.D. Pardridge to SLW., May 12, [no year]. (Box 57, Folder 12)
    - 2. Reprint from Advances in Biological and Medical Physics, vol.1, 1948, The Effects of the Atomic Bomb Irradiation on the Japanese, by Joe W. Howland and SLW., (12pp., including cover). (Box 57, Folder 12)
  - SLW Article With Letters., 1958.; 8 items:
    - 1. Copy mail record card, Dean's Office, UCLA School of Medicine, AMA Robert W. Riley, referred to Al Bellamy., August 18, 1958. (Box 57, Folder 13)
    - 2. Letter, Robert W. Riley to SLW., August 18, 1958. (Box 57, Folder 13)
    - 3. Copy rough draft of article by SLW., undated; (5pp.). (Box 57, Folder 13)
    - 4. Copy mail record card, Dean's Office, UCLA School of Medicine, Leslie R. Groves, referred to Bellamy., undated (Box 57, Folder 13)
    - 5. Letter, Leslie R. Groves to SLW., May 8, 1958.; (2pp.). (Box 57, Folder 13)
    - 6. Newspaper clipping on cover sheet, No Two-Headed Baby Salmon, New York Daily News., April 28, 1957. (Box 57, Folder 13)
    - 7. Copy letter, [SLW] to General Groves., undated (Box 57, Folder 13)
    - 8. Copy memo, by SLW., May 1, 1958.; (3pp.). (Box 57, Folder 13)
  - Copy report, Medical Problems of Atomic Bomb Testing, by SLW, presented to Brentwood Optimist Club., July 16, 1958.; (3 duplicates, 4pp. each) 1 item. (Box 57, Folder 14)
  - NBC White Paper: Decision to Drop the Bomb., December 1965.; 2 items:
    - 1. Copy cover letter for NBC White Paper script, Arnold L. Ahnfeld, Colonel, M.C. to SLW., February 4, 1965. (Box 57, Folder 15)
    - 2. Copy script, NBC White Paper: Decision to Drop the Bomb, reported by Chet Huntley, broadcast., January 5, 1965.; (57pp. including cover). (Box 57, Folder 15)
  - Copy letter (3pp.), SLW to Gavin Hadden, Armed Forces Special Weapons Project., June 17, 1948.; 1 item. (Box 57, Folder 16)
  - Periodical, Westways, vol.69 no.1 (42pp. including cover)., January 1977.; 1 item. (Box 57, Folder 17)
  - Science Magazine Clippings., December 1972.; 2 items:
    - 1. Clipping, article from Science, vol.178, Los Alamos: 30 Years after, Life Begins in Earnest, by Allen L. Hammond., December 8, 1972.; (2pp.). (Box 57, Folder 18)
    - 2. Clipping, article from Science, vol.178, Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory: Weapons Are still the Focus, by Allen L. Hammond., December 15, 1972.; (3pp.). (Box 57, Folder 18)
  - Letters and Reports., March 1979.; 5 items:
    - 1. Letter, Arnold Kramish to SLW., March 8, 1979.; (2pp.). (Box 57, Folder 19)
    - 2. Copy diary pages from General Grove's diary., September 4, 1944-September 5, 1944.; (5pp.). (Box 57, Folder 19)
    - 3. Rough note, Daghlian accident., May 21, 1946. (Box 57, Folder 19)
    - 4. Cover letter, John Seagrave to SLW., March 8, 1979. (Box 57, Folder 19)
    - 5. Copy report, Radiation Doses in the Pajarito Accident of, by Joseph G. Hoffman., May 21, 1946, May 26, 1948.; (26pp. including cover). (Box 57, Folder 19)
  - SLW Notebooks With Clippings., 1945.; 4 items:
    - 1. SLW notebook with separate rough notes enclosed., February 1945.; (14). (Box 57, Folder 20)
    - 2. SLW notebook with separate rough notes enclosed., November 1945.; (32). (Box 57, Folder 20)
    - 3. Newspaper clipping, Allies Must Finance Imports for Germany, Byrnes Declares, Washington Post, Associated Press., December 12, 1945. (Box 57, Folder 20)
    - 4. Newspaper clipping, Byrnes Leaves for Moscow Meeting Today, Washington Post, by Edward T. Folliard., December 12, 1945. (Box 57, Folder 20)
  - Rough list, photographs from Alamagordo., undated; 1 item. (Box 58, Folder 1)
  - Los Alamos Photographs., 2 items:
    - 1. Photograph, Los Alamos Photographic Laboratory, order number: 001055., undated (Box 58, Folder 2)
    - 2. Photographs, Los Alamos Photographic Laboratory, order number: 001055., undated; (8 duplicates). (Box 58, Folder 2)
  - Los Alamos Photographs., October 1, 1947.; 2 items:
    - 1. Photograph, Los Alamos Photographic Laboratory, order number: 001056., undated (Box 58, Folder 3)
    - 2. Photographs, 2 VT 428THAAFBU(S)(R)(1), Los Alamos Photographic Laboratory, order number: 001056., October 1, 1947.; (9 duplicates). (Box 58, Folder 3)
  - Los Alamos Photographs., 2 items:
    - 1. Photograph, Los Alamos Photographic Laboratory, order number: 001057., undated (Box 58, Folder 4)
    - 2. Photographs, Los Alamos Photographic Laboratory, order number: 001057., undated; (11 duplicates). (Box 58, Folder 4)
  - Los Alamos Photographs., October 1, 1947; 2 items:
    - 1. Photograph, Los Alamos Photographic Laboratory, order number: 001059., undated (Box 58, Folder 5)
    - 2. Photographs, OH 428 THAAFBU(S)(R)(1), Los Alamos Photographic Laboratory, order number: 001059., October 1, 1947.; (10 duplicates). (Box 58, Folder 5)
  - Los Alamos Photographs., October 1, 1947.; 2 items:
    - 1. Photograph, 1 VT 428 THAAFBU(S)(R)(1), Los Alamos Photographic Laboratory, order number: 001060., October 1, 1947. (Box 58, Folder 6)
    - 2. Photographs, 1 VT 428 THAAFBU(S)(R)(1), Los Alamos Photographic Laboratory, order number: 001060., October 1, 1947.; (11 duplicates). (Box 58, Folder 6)
  - Los Alamos Photographs., 2 items:
    - 1. Photograph, Los Alamos Photographic Laboratory, order number: 001062., undated (Box 58, Folder 7)
    - 2. Photographs, Los Alamos Photographic Laboratory, order number: 001062., undated; (10 duplicates). (Box 58, Folder 7)
  - Los Alamos Photographs., October 1, 1947; 2 items:
    - 1. Photographs, Los Alamos Photographic Laboratory, order number: 001063., undated; (2 duplicates). (Box 58, Folder 8)
    - 2. Photographs, 1 RT 428 THAAFBU(S)(R)(1), Los Alamos Photographic Laboratory, order number: 001063., October 1, 1947.; (10 duplicates). (Box 58, Folder 8)
  - Los Alamos Photographs., 2 items:
    - 1. Photograph, Los Alamos Photographic Laboratory, negative number: 5907., undated (Box 58, Folder 9)
    - 2. Photographs, Los Alamos Photographic Laboratory, order number: 5907., undated; (10 duplicates). (Box 58, Folder 9)
  - Los Alamos Photographs., 2 items:
    - 1. Photographs, Los Alamos Photographic Laboratory, order number: 5908., undated; (2 duplicates). (Box 58, Folder 10)
    - 2. Photographs, Los Alamos Photographic Laboratory, order number: 5908., undated; (9 duplicates). (Box 58, Folder 10)
  - Assorted Photographs, Test Area., 1948.; 128 items:
    - 1-13. Photographs with envelope., 1948.; 12 prints of Crater, 48 (13 items including envelope). (Box 58, Folder 11)
    - 14-48. Photographs with envelope, Test Area, Brauner pictures., undated; (35 items including envelope). (Box 58, Folder 11)
    - 49-63. Photographs with envelope, Test Area., undated; (15 items including envelope). (Box 58, Folder 11)
    - 64-80. Photographs with envelope, Effect of Bomb, Grass in Test Area., (17 items including envelope, plus duplicates). (Box 58, Folder 11)
    - 81-84. Photographs with envelope, Effect of Bomb, Russian Thistle from Test Area., 1950.; (4 items including envelope). (Box 58, Folder 11)
    - 85-95. Negatives with envelope, Weather Shelters., October 18, 1948.; (11 items including envelope). (Box 58, Folder 11)
    - 96-104. Negatives with envelope, General Views of Crater photographs by H.L. Lint., 1948.; (9 items including envelope). (Box 58, Folder 11)
    - Negatives with cover note, Trinity Site, plants, terrain, crater, weather shelters., undated; (18 items including cover note). (Box 58, Folder 11)
    - 105-120. Photographs with envelope, Miscellaneous Test Area., undated; (16 items including envelope). (Box 58, Folder 11)
    - 121-124. Negatives with cover note, Trinity., undated; (4 items including cover note). (Box 58, Folder 11)
    - 125-127. Negatives with cover note, Crater in, negatives for charts, by H. Lint., 1948.; (3 items including cover). (Box 58, Folder 11)
    - 128. Newspaper clipping, Intake Gates Shut: Twin Cities Cut off Radioactive Waters, Los Angeles Times, Part 1., November 22, 1971. (Box 58, Folder 11)
  - Assorted Charts and Sketches, Test Baker., July 1945.; 40 items:
    - 1-12. Sketch series, Pictorial Cloud Development, Test Baker, with rough cover note, by H.J. Summers., July 25, 1945.; (12 items, including cover). (Box 58, Folder 12)
    - 13-23. Copy sketch series, Pictorial Cloud Development, Test Baker, by H.J. Summers, July 25, 1945.; (11 items). (Box 58, Folder 12)
    - 24-34. Negative copy sketch series, Pictorial Cloud Development, Test Baker, by H.J. Summers., July 25, 1945.; (11 items). (Box 58, Folder 12)
    - 35-38. Copy graph series, Radioactive Cloud Rises., undated; (4 items). (Box 58, Folder 12)
    - 39. Copy chart, Daily Observations of Wind, Temperature, and Relative Humidity at Eniwetok., July 1945. (Box 58, Folder 12)
    - 40. Copy chart, Daily Observations of Wind, Temperature, and Relative Humidity at Eniwetok., August 1945. (Box 58, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper Clipping With Sketches., 1945, 1978.; 11 items:
    - 1. Newspaper clipping, Arthur E. Beaumont, Noted Marine Artist, Dies at 87, Los Angeles Times., January 24, 1978. (Box 58, Folder 13)
    - 2. Sketch series, Alamagordo, New Mexico Atomic Bomb Test, by H.J. Summers., July 16, 1945.; (10 items). (Box 58, Folder 13)
  - Assorted Reports, Radiation as a Weapon., 1943.; 6 items:
    - 1. Negative copy report, Radiation as a War Weapon, by SLW to Dr. James B. Conant., July 27, 1943.; (5pp.). (Box 58, Folder 14)
    - 2. Cover sheet, University of Rochester Atomic Energy Project, File VI-510, Unit no.113 for Radioactive Spray and Dust report., undated (Box 58, Folder 14)
    - 3. Copy report, Practical Tests of the Application of Highly Radioactive Sprays and Dust to Level Ground and to Buildings, by Harold C. Hodge, PhD, toxicologist and William F. Bale, PhD, consultant., August 6, 1943.; (16pp. including cover). (Box 58, Folder 14)
    - 4. Cover sheet, War Department for Report on Radiation Experiment., undated (Box 58, Folder 14)
    - 5. Copy Instructions, Treatment of Secret Reports., undated (Box 58, Folder 14)
    - 6. Copy report, Report on Radiation Experiments, by William F. Bale., July 21, 1943.; (6pp.). (Box 58, Folder 14)
  - Reports, Photographs and Sketches: Blast Waves., 1951; 5 items: